Inventory of the William L. Connelly papers, 1904-1964
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
William L. Connelly papers
1904-1964
Connelly, William L., 1873-1964
01722
3.50 cubic feet (7 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Scrapbooks, photographs, writings, and research material of an oil industry executive whose career with Sinclair Oil began in 1906 and who headed Mammoth Oil Company in Wyoming during the Teapot Dome scandal.
Biography of William L. Connelly
W.L. Connelly (1873-1964) was a pioneer of the American oil industry, whose career spanned 73 years. He drilled his first well in 1895 in Wood County, Ohio. He did oil work in Montgomery County, Kansas from 1903-1905. In early 1906 he became associated with Harry F. Sinclair. Connelly moved to Tulsa Oklahoma with Sinclair in 1912. In 1916 he was one of the founders of Sinclair Oil and Refining Company and became president of the subsidiary Sinclair-Cudahy Pipeline Company. He moved to Houston in 1917, where he was vice president of Sinclair Gulf Oil Corporation with responsibility for operations in Mexico. Between 1922 and 1928 he was stationed in Casper, Wyoming, as president of Mammoth Oil Company. This was during the period of the Teapot Dome scandal. He was then promoted to vice president of Sinclair Consolidated Oil Corporation and president of Venezuelan Petroleum Corporation. In this capacity he oversaw operations in Mexico, Venezuela, and Africa from a base in New York City. In 1932 Sinclair Oil merged with Prairie Oil and Gas Company, and Connelly became chairman of the board (1932-1950).
William L. Connelly married Elizabeth Conlisk in Toledo, Ohio, in 1898. The couple had a daughter and a son. In 1933 he received the rank of Knight Commander of the Knights of the Holy Sepulchre from Pope Pius XI. Connelly published a book on his experiences in the oil industry, "The Oil Business As I Saw It," in 1955. During his life he traveled to Europe, Russia, Turkey, South America, Mexico, and the Caribbean to pursue business, as well as to pursue his favorite hobby of fishing.
Scope and Content
The collection includes narratives of trips to Mexico, Russia, Europe, Africa, Caribbean Islands, and Venezuela. Also included are scrapbooks, photographs, and photograph albums documenting Connelly's career in the oil industry and his personal life, including his travels and his investiture as a Knight of the Holy Sepulchre. The Teapot Dome scandal is covered in photographs and newspaper clippings. There is also information about Harry F. Sinclair and other prominent men in the oil industry. In addition there are records of oil companies that were absorbed into Sinclair Corporation, including Kathleen Oil Company, Numa Oil Company, Lucas Oil Company, Oil Production Company, and Mammoth Oil Company, among others.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by William L. Connelly at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The material was received from Harry S. Connelly and from the Sinclair Oil Corporation in 1965 and 1966.
Access Terms
Sinclair, Harry Ford, 1876-; Connelly family.; Sinclair Oil Corporation.; Sinclair Investment Company.; Kathleen Oil Company.; Numa Oil Company.; Lucas Oil Company.; Oil Production Company.; Mammoth Oil Company.; Teapot Dome Scandal, 1921-1924.; Petroleum industry and trade -- Oklahoma.; Casper (Wyo.) -- History.; Tulsa (Okla.) -- History.; Tulsa (Okla.) -- Genealogy.; Business records.; Diaries.; Genealogies.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Businessmen.
Mines and Mineral Resources; Energy Production; Business, Industry, Labor, and Commerce; Businesses and Corporations
Container List
- Series I. Personal and Family Materials
  - Biographical Information, 1937-1960 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical Material and Personal Correspondence, 1956-1963 (Box 1)
  - Knights of the Holy Sepulchre (correspondence and certificates), 1936-1950 (Box 1)
  - Printed Material, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Travel Narratives:
    - Europe-Turkey-Russia, 1923 (Box 1)
    - Caribbean-South America (Venezuelan Petroleum Company), 1929 (Box 1)
    - Europe-Africa (Companhia de Petroleo de Angola), 1929 (Box 1)
    - Spain, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Tampico, Mexico (fishing), 1955 (Box 1)
    - Caribbean-Venezuela, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Eighth Pass, Mexico - "The Trial of 'Bear' Gracey" (fishing), undated (Box 1)
- Series II. Oil Industry Records
  - Companies:
    - Aurora Oil & Gas Company, 1909-1916 (Box 1)
    - Byers Drilling Company, 1913-1920 (Box 1)
    - Cheyenne Oil Company, 1913-1918 (Box 1)
    - Galbraith Drilling Company, 1909-1920 (Box 1)
    - Kathleen Oil Company, 1910-1922 (Box 1)
    - Kiester Drilling Company, 1913-1920 (Box 1)
    - Lucas Oil Company, 1908-1919 (Box 1)
    - Numa Oil Company, 1910-1921 (Box 1)
    - Oil Production Company, 1912-1918 (Box 1)
    - Palermo Oil Company; Scioto Oil Company; Richards Drilling Company, 1913-1919 (Box 1)
    - Sinclair Oil Company, 1904-1921 (Box 1)
    - Sinclair Oil Company - Printed Material ("Oil-And Independence!: The Story of the Sinclair Oil Corporation," by P.C. Spencer; "The Oil Strike: A Factual Statement of the Issues Involved," by H.F. Sinclair), 1957, undated (Box 1)
  - Diagram - Crosscut Tunnel, 1931 (Box 3)
  - Index: Corporations (notebook), undated (Box 2)
  - Index: Dissolved Corporations (notebook), undated (Box 2)
- Series III. Photographs and Photograph Albums
  - Album of W.L. Connelly's Career, circa 1920-1930 (Box 2)
  - Album of W.L. Connelly's Career - Teapot Dome (loose photos), 1920s (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L., circa 1920s-1960s (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - and Others, 1950s (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - at Events, 1953-1962 (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Family, 1950-1963 (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Fishing, Hunting, Camping, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Knights of the Holy Sepulchre, 1941-1950 (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - 90th Birthday, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Sinclair 40-year Banquet, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Teapot Dome Court Case, 1920s (Box 2)
  - Connelly, W.L. - With Groups, 1907-1958 (Box 2)
  - Gutierrez Lease; Zurita Lease; Panuco Steamer; New Orleans Warehouses (photo album and loose duplicates), 1918-1919 (Box 2)
  - Oil Well Fires (Venezuela; Oklahoma), 1928, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Sinclair, H.F. (inscribed), undated (Box 2)
- Series IV. Scrapbooks
  Scrapbooks contain newspaper and magazine clippings, correspondence, photographs, and other items.
  - Connelly, W.L. - Life and Career, 1910-1958 (Box 3)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Life and Career, 1922-1963 (Box 4)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Life and Career (publication of book), 1954-1961 (Box 7)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Life and Career (honors), 1958-1961 (Box 5)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Life and Career (honors), 1959 (Box 5)
  - Connelly, W.L. - Life and Career, 1928, 1959-1964 (Box 7)
  - Sinclair Oil, 1929-1942 (Box 6)
  - Teapot Dome, 1922-1930, 1962 (Box 6)
  - Teapot Dome - Court Case, 1925-1933 (Box 6)